William Berry Hartsfield papers, circa 1860s-1983
Emory University
William Berry Hartsfield papers, circa 1860s-1983
Hartsfield, William Berry.
Manuscript Collection No. 558
38.25 linear ft. (79 boxes), 78 oversized papers (OP), 12 bound volumes (BV), and 2 oversized bound volumes (OBV)
Papers of Atlanta mayor William Berry Hartsfield including personal papers, correspondence, subject files, writings, printed material, photographs, memorabilia, and audiovisual material.
Emory University Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library
Source
Gift, with subsequent additions.
Restrictions on Access
Researchers must contact MARBL in advance to access audiovisual materials in this collection.
Biographical Note
William Berry Hartsfield (March 1, 1890-February 22, 1971), attorney, politician, and mayor of Atlanta was born in Atlanta, Georgia, the son of Charles Green Hartsfield, a tinsmith, and Victoria Dagnall Hartsfield. He married Pearl Williams on August 2, 1913 and they had two children, William Berry Hartsfield, Jr. and Mildred Hartsfield Cheshire. They divorced after forty-eight years of marriage and Hartsfield married Tollie Tolan on July 11, 1962. He later adopted her son, Carl.
Hartsfield attended Boys High School in Atlanta and found employment as a clerk for the General Fire Extinguisher Company. In 1916, while working as a clerk for the legal firm of Rosser, Slaton, Phillips, and Hopkins, he began reading law. His formal education was completed in 1937, when the Atlanta Law School awarded him a Bachelor of Law degree. Hartsfield was admitted to the Georgia Bar in 1917 and established a practice in Atlanta. His first entrance into the political arena came in 1923, with his election to the City Council of Atlanta. He remained a council member until 1928. During this time, he served on the municipal airport committee and helped arrange the purchase of Candler Field as the site for the city's first municipal airport. The Hartsfield International Airport is named in his honor.
From 1933 to 1937, Hartsfield served as a Fulton County Representative to the Georgia Legislature. In 1936, he defeated incumbent Mayor James L. Key in the first of the seven mayoral elections he entered. With the exception of an eighteen-month period in 1941-1942, Hartsfield served as the city's chief administrator continuously from 1937 to 1962. As mayor, Hartsfield saw the city more than triple in land area, grow to have over a million inhabitants, and survive the Depression and World War II fiscally sound and ready to undertake such civic improvements as building expressways and city parks. An early racial moderate, he guided the city through the 1950s and the beginnings of the Civil Rights Movement. Hartsfield also served as an officer in two mining companies, the Southern Talc Company of Atlanta and Chatsworth, Georgia (1933-1942) and the Georgia Lightweight Aggregate Company (1951-1954). Throughout most of his life, he maintained an interest in Georgia's mineral development.
Following Hartsfield's retirement from city government in 1962, he was named Mayor Emeritus and became a consultant to the Ford Foundation's Committee of Review and Evaluation, Urban Program; to the Rockefeller Foundation's Performing Arts Panel; and to the Coca Cola Company. He was also named president of the Southeastern Fair Association. A life-long member of the First Baptist Church of Atlanta, Hartsfield was also a Democrat, a Mason, and a Shriner. Among the many honors he received were honorary Doctorate of Law degrees from Oglethorpe University and Atlanta University, both in 1961.
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of the papers of William B. Hartsfield from circa 1860-1983. The papers include personal papers, correspondence, subject files, writings by Hartsfield (speeches and articles), pamphlets, newspaper clippings, magazine articles, photographs, memorabilia, and audiovisual materials. The bulk of the collection dates from the mid-1930s to the time of his death in 1971.
The Hartsfield papers document Hartsfield's political, business, and personal life. Materials relating to his 23 years as mayor are extensive and can be found in every series. Particularly valuable are the election materials in Series 3: Election files, which include notes about campaign tactics, correspondence, literature, and financial records for his seven mayoral elections. The personal papers, correspondence, subject files, and photograph series illustrate the importance politics played in his life. Hartsfield's business interests are revealed in Series 1: Personal papers and Series 6: Personal Business records. Material relating to his personal life, including family correspondence and financial records, is in Series 1: Personal papers.
Other topics covered by the papers are the growth of commercial aviation in Atlanta; annexation of Buckhead and Sandy Springs; Chattahoochee River development and the building of the Buford Dam to assure the city's water supply; the 1939 Gone with The Wind premiere; race relations in the city in the 1940s, 1950s, and early 1960s (from hiring the first black policemen to integrating Atlanta schools); Hartsfield's fight to prevent the fluoridation of Atlanta's water; the growth of performing arts in Atlanta; and, in general, the evolution of Atlanta into a major metropolitan area.
Major correspondents include political and business leaders of Atlanta, Georgia, governors, senators, congressmen, national political figures, and persons active in the motion picture and mining industries. Among the names represented in the correspondence are Ivan Allen, Jr., Henry L. Bowden, Helen Bullard, Lester Maddox, Everett Millican, Ralph McGill, Lawrence "Chip" Robert, Richard Russell, David O. Selznick, Herman Talmadge, and Robert W. Woodruff.
Arrangement Note
Organized into eleven series: (1) Personal papers, (2) Correspondence, (3) Elections, (4) Subject files (5) Writings, (6) Personal business records, (7) Printed materials, (8) Photographs, (9) Memorabilia, (10) Moses Cox files, and (11) Audiovisual materials.
Finding Aid Note
An index to selected correspondence in this collection is available.
Selected Search Terms
Uniform Title
Gone with the wind (Motion picture)
Personal Names
Allen, Ivan.; Bullard, Helen, 1908-1979.; Maddox, Lester, 1915-2003.; McGill, Ralph, 1898-1969.; Robert, Lawrence Wood, 1889-1976.; Russell, Richard B. (Richard Brevard), 1897-1971.; Selznick, David O., 1902-1965.; Talmadge, Herman E. (Herman Eugene), 1913-2002.; Woodruff, Robert Winship.
Corporate Names
Atlanta (Ga.). Mayor.; Southern Talc Company.
Topical Terms
Elections--Georgia.; Mines and mineral resources--Georgia.; Motion pictures--Georgia.; Municipal government--Georgia.; Municipal water supply--Georgia.; Talc industry--Georgia.; Water--Fluoridation--Georgia.
Geographic Names
Atlanta (Ga.)--Politics and government.; Atlanta (Ga.)--Race relations.; Atlanta (Ga.)--Transportation--Aviation.; Georgia--Politics and government--1865-1950.; Georgia--Politics and government--1951-; Georgia--Race relations.; Georgia--Transportation--Aviation.
Form/Genre Terms
Motion pictures.; Sound recordings.
Description of Series
- Personal papers, 1918-1986, Series 1; Boxes 1-9; OP 1-8, 57-58; OBV 1
  Scope and Content Note
  The series contains materials concerning members of the Hartsfield family, including biographical material, calendars, legal records, and correspondence to and from family members. Biographical data includes Hartsfield family genealogical records, subject files relating to dependents of William B. Hartsfield, and biographical sketches of William B. Hartsfield. Correspondence includes letters to and from Hartsfield family members, including correspondence between Hartsfield and his second wife Tollie Tolan. Tolan's correspondence makes up approximately half of the family correspondence, spanning the periods before her marriage to Hartsfield and after his death (1940-1986). Her correspondence is comprised of love letters from Hartsfield, communication regarding social and political engagements, letters to and from friends and family, and sympathy letters following Hartsfield's death in 1971. Correspondence relating to Hartsfield's political career as mayor may be found in Series 2: Correspondence.
  Calendars were kept by William Hartsfield and contain appointments and other notations. Financial records pertain mostly to Hartsfield and contain banking records (including paycheck stubs showing Hartsfield's salary as mayor), income tax reports, investments, and records of travel reimbursements from the city of Atlanta. Financial records relating to election campaigns and mineral investments can be found in the appropriate subject files in Series 3: Elections and Series 6: Personal business records. Legal records in this series include financial documents; wills and estates; passports and birth certificates; property mortgages; military, education, and employment documents; and other legal documents. The records pertain mainly to Hartsfield, Tollie Tolan (Mrs. W.B. Hartsfield), and their adopted son, Carl Siegfried Hartsfield. Several documents concerning estates and wills pertain to other members of the Hartsfield family.
  Arrangement Note
  Arranged by record type.
  Finding Aid Note
  An index to selected correspondence in this series is available.
  - Biographical records
  - Bettis, Fannie Lee (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Hartsfield family genealogical correspondence (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Hartsfield family genealogical records (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1918-1975, Series 2; Boxes 10-16
  This series contains Hartsfield's professional and political correspondence. The remainder of Hartsfield's correspondence is scattered throughout the rest of the collection. For his correspondence to, from, and directly regarding family members, see Series 1: Personal papers; for correspondence relating to elections, see Series 3: Elections; for correspondence regarding his personal business interests, see Series 6: Personal business records; for all other subjects see Hartsfield's subject files located in Series 4.
  The majority of the correspondence in this series is from his time as mayor (1937-1961). A much smaller amount of material is from pre-mayoral (1918-1936) and post-mayoral (1962-1971) periods; letters posted to him after his death are also included (1971-1975). Pre-mayoral correspondence includes letters relating to his law office and letters to and from friends. Mayoral correspondence includes letters to and from local and national politicians, correspondence relating to political and social issues, V-mail written by Atlantans serving in World War II, postcards from friends traveling in foreign countries, routine correspondence about business travel, congratulatory letters, birthday and Christmas greetings, event invitations, thank-you letters, and other matters. Correspondents include well-known political advisors Everett Millican and Helen Bullard.
  Arranged in chronological order.
  - Pre-mayoral correspondence
  - October 1918-December 1933 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - January 1934-December 1936 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Mayoral correspondence
  - January 1937-December 1939 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - January 1940-May 1941 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - June-December 1941 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - January-June 1942 (Box 10, Folder 6)
- Election files, 1932-1970s, Series 3; Boxes 17-25; OP 9-24, 58-63
  This series contains materials related to Hartsfield's political campaigns from 1932 to the 1970s. Materials include correspondence; campaign lists, schedules, and notes; financial records; campaign advertisements; newspaper clippings; political cartoons; and speeches. The series also contains materials Hartsfield and his campaign staff collected about opposition candidates. Arranged by election, the series ranges from one of Hartsfield's earliest elections as the Fulton County Representative to the Georgia Legislature in 1932 to his campaigns for mayor of Atlanta from 1936-1957.
  Correspondence includes letters of support from constituents, memos from political consultants such as Helen Bullard, and correspondence from opposition campaigns sent to Hartsfield. Most letters also include a copy of Hartsfield's response. Campaign lists and notes consist of lists of people to contact and notes about campaign strategy. Newspaper clippings are mostly from the Atlanta Journal and include appearances, editorials, political cartoons, and election results. The series also contains a few original, hand-drawn "Baldy" political cartoons. Speeches include those of Hartsfield and his opposition. Many were broadcast on WSB radio
  Materials in this series document issues of public interest in Atlanta. Public housing, annexation, police department policies and activities, and expansion of the airport were all debated in mayoral races. Hartsfield's moderate racial stance was a major election issue as well. After the white primary was outlawed in the mid-1940s, Hartsfield won most of his elections by building coalitions of white and black voters, a strategy documented in the campaign literature and campaign notes in this series.
  Arranged in chronological order by election.
  - Legislative races, 1932-1934
  - Campaign advertisements, 1932-1934 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Campaign lists and notes (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1932-1934 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Financial records (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Newspaper clippings, Bulletin, May 12, 1932, July 1932 [entire issues] (Box OP9)
- Subject files, 1906-1982, Series 4; Boxes 26-38; OP 25-28, 64-67; BV 1-3
  This series consists of subject files relating to Hartsfield's wide and varied interests in the city of Atlanta, primarily from his time as Mayor and Mayor Emeritus (1937-1970). Correspondence, newspaper clippings, reports, programs, and other collected materials make up the series. Prominent topics include operations of the Atlanta City Government, Hartsfield's investigation of fluoridation and his battle against fluoridation of Atlanta's water system, correspondence and programs related to the world premiere of Gone with the Wind in Atlanta, and development of the Hartsfield International Airport. Other subjects include the annexation of Buckhead, school desegregation, Hartsfield's nomination for the Assistant Secretary for Aeronautics in the U.S. Commerce Department, consultation work with the Ford and Rockefeller Foundations, and his role in promoting the Atlanta Symphony Guild.
  Arranged in alphabetical order.
  - Alcohol, 1960s (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - American Society of Civil Engineers, 1950-1954, correspondence and reports (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - American Society of Civil Engineers, 1950-1954, reports (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - Amusement parks, 1957, 1960 (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - Atlanta Annexation, general, Buckhead, Sandy Springs, 1940s-1960s (Box 26, Folder 5)
  - Atlanta Arts Alliance, 1960s-1980s (Box 26, Folder 6)
- Writings, 1937-1980, Series 5; Box 39
  This series contains writings by Hartsfield and others. Writings by Hartsfield make up the bulk of this series, the majority dating from his twenty-three years as mayor and his ten years as Mayor Emeritus (1937-1970). His writings include speeches and public statements made as both Mayor and private citizen. A volume of his addresses to the General Board of the City of Atlanta and to the city's Board of Aldermen (1937-1962) is found here, as are four small notebooks of diary entries about travels to Europe and Japan (1950s-1970). His campaign speeches may be found in Series 3: Elections. Writings by others make up a smaller portion of this series, including article drafts, speeches, and scripts for television and radio broadcasts featuring Hartsfield.
  - Hartsfield, William B.
  - "Annual Addresses" (bound volume), 1937-1962 (Box 39, Folder 1)
  - Annual and Final Message of Mayor William B. Hartsfield, January 2, 1962 (with notes) (Box 39, Folder 2)
  - Interview with Hartsfield, transcript, sit-ins of the 1960s, January 6, 1966 (Box 39, Folder 3)
  - Speeches, 1930s-1947 (Box 39, Folder 4)
- Personal business records, 1929-1970, Series 6; Boxes 40-49
  This series contains the personal business records of Hartsfield. In addition to his work as Mayor of Atlanta, Hartsfield maintained an active interest in the development of Georgia's mineral and mining activities. He helped to found the Southern Talc Company in 1933, serving as its president throughout the 1930s and 1940s. This series contains the business records of the Southern Talc Company and documents Hartsfield's work in that company. The series also contains Hartsfield's subject files on minerals and mining in Georgia.
  Organized into two subseries: (6.1) Minerals and mining files and (6.2) Southern Talc Company records.
  - Minerals and mining files, 1929-1970, Subseries 6.1; Boxes 40-44
    This subseries contains subject files related to Hartsfield's interest in minerals and mining, his primary non-Atlanta and non-mayoral pastime. From the early 1930s through the late 1950s, Hartsfield maintained an active interest in the development of Georgia's mineral industries, occasionally investing in mining ventures. He investigated the possibility of drilling for oil in the north Georgia mountains and bought shares in talc, mica, and phosphate mines. He was also a founder and director of the Georgia Lightweight Aggregate Company, 1951-1954. Hartsfield never achieved the financial success he desired and, by the time of his retirement from politics, he had turned his attentions elsewhere. This subseries consists mostly of correspondence, although there are occasional financial records, newspaper clippings, and published reports among the correspondence in the files.
    - Bentonite clay, 1934-1953 (Box 40, Folder 1)
    - Brecon Loading Company, 1941-1946 (Box 40, Folder 2)
    - Chromite (Louise Property, Troupe County, Ga.), 1942- March 1943 (Box 40, Folder 3)
    - Chromite (Louise Property, Troupe County, Ga.), April 1943-1949 (Box 40, Folder 4)
    - Columbia, South America, prospecting, 1955-1959 (Box 40, Folder 5)
    - Flagstone, 1941 (Box 40, Folder 6)
    - Fuller's Earth (clay), 1953-1954 (Box 40, Folder 7)
  - Southern Talc Company records, 1934-1949, Subseries 6.2; Boxes 45-49
    This series contains the records of the Southern Talc Company of Atlanta and Chatsworth, Georgia. The company was incorporated in 1933 and sold in 1942. Hartsfield helped organize the company and served as legal counsel and president. This was apparently Hartsfield's first major business venture and the only time he played such an active role in guiding the affairs of a company. Included among the company's papers are letters advertising the talc for sale; correspondence with sales agents and purchasers; inventories; purchasing orders; receipts; and correspondence between Hartsfield, T.N. Brooks, and V.C. Pickering, fellow officers of the Company. The Southern Talc Company was a small mining company which battled both the sluggish economy of the Depression and the mineral use restrictions of the first years of World War II and was only a limited financial success. This subseries consists mostly of correspondence, with scattered blueprints, reports, and financial records.
    - Advertisements (Box 45, Folder 1)
    - Agents (sales), 1935-1940 (Box 45, Folder 2)
    - American Cyanamid Company, 1936-1940 (Box 45, Folder 3)
    - Atlanta Freight Bureau, 1937-1940 (Box 45, Folder 4)
- Printed material, circa 1920-1983, Series 7; Boxes 50-55; OP 29-33; BV 4
  This series contains collected printed material about Hartsfield and materials collected by him. Hartsfield saved many magazine and newspaper articles, pamphlets, and reports relating to himself and to the government and welfare of Atlanta. These include magazine, periodical, and newspaper clippings; pamphlets, flyers, and reports of various Atlanta organizations; and event programs. Magazine and newspaper clippings featuring Hartsfield are listed separately from general clippings. Programs commemorate public events attended by Hartsfield, including dedications, awards ceremonies, and dinners. Among the many topics, issues, and events dating from the 1920s to the early 1980s documented in this series are Atlanta roadways and traffic, elections of Atlanta government officials, local crime, aviation, and debate on local legislature. A large number of political cartoons are also found in this series. For additional printed material arranged by subject, see Series 4: Subject Files.
  Articles and clippings arranged in chronological order; pamphlets and reports arranged in alphabetical order.
  - Clippings, William B. Hartsfield
  - Magazines and periodicals, 1940s (Box 50, Folder 1)
  - Magazines and periodicals, 1950s (Box 50, Folder 2)
  - Magazines and periodicals, 1960-1964 (Box 50, Folder 3)
  - Magazines and periodicals, May 1961 (Box OP29)
- Photographs, circa 1960s-1970s, Series 8; Boxes 56-65; OP 34-56, 68-76; BV 5-12; OBV 2
  This series contains photographs of William B. Hartsfield, his family, other politicians and national figures, and Atlanta events from the 1860s to the 1970s. The bulk of this series highlights the ceremonial duties of the mayor of a growing American city (1930s-1971). Welcoming Hollywood stars and city visitors, cutting ribbons for grand openings, and attending dinners and banquets are well-photographed mayoral duties. Other events are Gone with the Wind premieres; travels to Europe and South America; meetings with Presidents, politicians, the Pope, and others; various stages in the development of the Chattahoochee River and Buford Dam water systems; the expansion of the airport; and several inaugural air flights on which Hartsfield was a passenger. Portrait photographs of Hartsfield from childhood to shortly before his death are also included in this series (1892-1971). There is also a large collection of family and other personal photographs (circa 1860s-1960s). Tollie Tolan Hartsfield's personal photographs (circa 1890s-1970s), also located in this series, contain few pictures related to Mayor Hartsfield. They primarily show scenes of friends, family, and vacations from before her marriage to Hartsfield and after his death. Eight photograph albums of ceremonial events, such as the launching of the U.S.S. Atlanta and the dedication of St. Joseph's Hospital, are also included in this series.
  Arranged in alphabetical order by subject.
  - William B. Hartsfield portraits
  - 1892-1919 (Box 56, Folder 1)
  - 1920-1949 (Box 56, Folder 2)
  - 1940s (Box OP68)
  - 1950s (Box OP68)
  - 1950-1956 (Box 56, Folder 3)
- Memorabilia, 1930s-1972, Series 9; Boxes 66-71, OP 77
  The memorabilia series contains various objects collected by Hartsfield during his political career and after his retirement. Included are multiple keys to cities, including two oversized wooden keys given to Hartsfield by Atlanta residents, two gavels, and cards from various businesses and civic associations. There is also a substantial amount of campaign ephemera, including buttons, combs, match books, nail files, and thimbles, from local, state and federal political campaigns. Ribbons, medals and name tags show Hartsfield's many associations and involvement in regional conferences. Tickets, name tags and visitor passes shed light on Hartsfield's travels to Democratic National Conventions, Congress, the White House, and events he attended, such as the launching of Apollo 12. There is also a pen in the collection from the White House which was possibly used by President Lyndon B. Johnson to sign the 1964 Civil Rights Bill into law.
  Arranged by material type.
  - Advertisement, Southeastern Fair, Atlanta, undated (Box 66, Folder 1)
  - Artificial money, Twe dollar bill [sic], anti-paper money arguments, Liberty Books, St. Louis, Missouri, undated (Box 66, Folder 2)